اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝
بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
The delegates, a few of the Arab tribes came to Madina
to negotiate with the Khalifah(خليفه) of the Muslims, Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
They said: We never gave up Islam.
we bear witness and we testify that there is no God but Allah
and that Muhammad(محمد) is the Messenger of Allah
and we will pray to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, but by no means, are we going to pay you Zaka'at(زكوة).
And these Arab tribes sent very high level, delegates
people with some old connections with notables of Madina.
So the Friends of this leader in Madina would stay with him
and the friends of this leader would stay with him.
So they weren't only negotiating with the Khalifah(خليفه) directly
but also they had some of the notables of the Muslims, speaking on their behalf.
And all of this pressure was mounting on the Khalifah(خليفه).
Plus, from a religious standpoint, it wasn't very clear to the Sahabah(صحابه) yet.
So even Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه was discussing this with Al-Khalifah(خليفه) - Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Now with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), it's not at all because he was pressured
by some of these tribes or because he had some relationship with them. No!
He was arguing from his understanding of the Sharia(شريعة) evidence.
So he went to the Khalifah(خليفه) and said, and this is in Bukhari(بخاريْ):
كيفَ تُقَاتِلُ النَّاسَ؟
وقدْ قالَ رَسولُ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللهُ عليه وسلَّمَ
أُمِرْتُ أنْ أُقَاتِلَ النَّاسَ حتَّى يقولوا: لا إلَهَ إلَّا اللَّهُ،
فمَن قالَهَا فقَدْ عَصَمَ مِنِّي مَالَهُ ونَفْسَهُ إلَّا بحَقِّهِ، وحِسَابُهُ علَى اللَّهِ
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: How can you fight them.?
When Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
I was commanded by Allah to fight the people, until they testify that there is no God but Allah.
If they do, then they have protected themselves, and their wealth.
Now this Hadith(حديث) of,
أُمِرْتُ أنْ أُقَاتِلَ النَّاسَ
Came in various forums, but the Hadith(حديث) is Mutawatir(متواتر)
the highest level of Hadith(حديث).
Hadith(حديث) that is Mutawatir(متواتر) is a Hadith(حديث) that is narrated, through so many chains of narration,
it becomes impossible to refute
it is the highest level of authenticity.
This Hadith(حديث) was mentioned by so many Sahabah(صحابه), just to name some:
Abu Hurairah رضي الله عنه, Anas Ibn Malik(أنس إبن مالك), Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس),
An-Nauman Bin Masheer(ألنعمان بن مشير), many, I think more than 20 Sahabah(صحابه) narrated it.
And it's in, Bukhari(بخاريْ), Muslim(مسلم), Abu Daud(أبوداؤد), Tirmidhi(ترمذي), An-Nisae(ألنسائ),
Ibn Majah(إبن ماجه), Al-Hakim(ألحاكم), Ad-Darimi(ألدارمي), At-Tabraani(أطبراني)
Masnad Al-Imam Ahmad(مسنداِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ).
So the Hadith(حديث) is very strong, and the Nuss(نص) of the Hadith(حديث) is
I was instructed to fight the people, until they testify that there is no God but Allah.
Now, when this Hadith(حديث) is mentioned, people think that it contradicts the Ayah(آية) of Qur'an
لَآ إِكْرَاهَ فِى ٱلدِّينِ ۖ
There is no compulsion in religion
because the Ayah(آية) says: There is no compulsion in religion.
While this Hadith(حديث) says;
I was instructed to fight the people until they testify that there's no God but Allah
and that Muhammad(محمد) is the Messenger of Allah and in another narration.
ويقيموا الصلواة ويؤتوا الزكوة
And they pray and they pay Zaka'at(زكوة).
So, how do we combine between these two Nuss(نص) - text.
Well, there were quite a few different interpretations, given by scholars,
referring to this Hadith(حديث), one of them is that;
Rasool Allah ﷺ was instructed to fight the people
until they accept either Islam or Jizya(جزية).
So by accepting Jizya(جزية) even though they didn't become Muslim
they have accepted the rule of Islam
they accepted the Hukum(حكم) of Allah.
And that the whole earth needs to be ruled by the law of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
But then as individuals, Islam cannot be forced on them.
So you cannot force a religion on a person
because it's an issue that goes back to the conviction
its - من أعمال القلب - it's something that is in the heart of a person.
You cannot force a person to be convinced in something.
Therefore there is no - إِكْرَاهَ فِى ٱلدِّينِ ۖ - but in terms of the law of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ,
people need to be fought until the law of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is established.
Anyway, so Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) goes to the Khalifah(خليفه) and says;
How can you fight them, they are saying;
أشهدو ان لا إله إلا الله، واشهدو ان محمدًا رسول الله
And they're praying, how can you fight them?
Now, neither did Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) nor did Umar(عُمَر)
hear about the different narration of the Hadith(حديث)
that says and they pray and they pay Zaka'at(زكوة),
because if they did, then there wouldn't be any argument.
What was the responsible of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه?
He said;
واللهِ لَأُقاتِلَنَّ مَن فرَّق بيْنَ الصَّلاةِ والزَّكاةِ؛
فإنَّ الزكاةَ حَقُّ المالِ ، واللهِ لو مَنَعُونِي عَنَاقًا كانوا يُؤَدُّونها إلى رسولِ الله صلَّى اللهُ عليه وسلَّمَ لَقاتَلْتُهم على مَنْعِها
He said: In the name of Allah, I will fight whoever differentiates between Salah(صلاة) and Zaka'at(زكوة).
And if they prevent me one camel
and in another narration, a rope that you tie the neck of a camel with if they prevent me that
and they used to pay it Rasool Allah ﷺ, I'm gonna fight them over it.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
When I saw the conviction of Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق)
I realized that this is the truth.
So again Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) here is setting the rules for the Khulafa(خلفاء) after him.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) here is wondering whether a person after the Prophet Muhammadﷺ has a right
to fight against people who are claiming to be Muslim,
but they're not fulfilling all of the Ahkaam(أحكام) of Islam, Al-Faraidh(ألفرائض).
But Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) is saying that
that is part of the authority of the Khalifah(خليفه).
That is part of the authority of the person, who is taking the position of Rasool Allah ﷺ after he passes away.
And he is telling the Khulafah(خلفاء) after him, that it is your responsibility to enforce the law of Islam,
even if the people who break it claim to be Muslim.
So this is another case an example where the Fiqh(فقه) of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه prevails
and it is established as Al-Haqq(ألحق)
even by the people who are against him like Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
Umar(عُمَر) said, that I came to realize that his opinion was right opinion.
So all of these again are issues relating to the Islamic politics
if you could call it
or the authority that is given to the Muslim leader.
So Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is establishing a Sunnah(سنة)
he made this clear to all of the delegates and they left without any agreement.
Now Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he went to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه and he said;
يا خليفة رسول الله تعلف الناس ورفق بهم
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: O, Khalifah(خليفه) of Rasool Ullah
تعلف الناس
bring them close,
ورفق بهم
be lenient with them.
You know, because of the condition that we are in,
you need to be lenient, you need to give and take with the people,
you need to show them a soft side.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه obviously you would find this statement strange to come from Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
thats not the Umar(عمر) that we know.
But Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was keeping in mind the circumstances of the situation,
I mean, Madina is in danger
the entire religion is in danger,
the Muslim community is in danger
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is not saying to negotiate on issues of religion
but he's just saying that, be a bit more lenient with these tribes
they are claiming to be Muslim.
So, give and take with them and try to reach a deal.
What was the response of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)?
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) grabbed the beard of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and he said;
يا أبن الخطاب : ألجبارٌ في الجاهلية خوارٌ في الإسلام
He said: O, Son of Khattab(خطاب), you were a tyrant, before you became Muslim.
And now when you became Muslim, you want to become lame, feeble and weak.
And then he said;
إنه قد انقطع الوحي وتم الدين أينقص وأنا حي ؟
He said, the religion has been left by Muhammadﷺ complete.
Do you think that I will allow it to decrease, while I'm still alive.
I'm not gonna allow the religion of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to diminish.
I'm not gonna allow it to go down while I'm still alive.
As long as I'm alive, I'm going to fight for this religion.
So, Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه whom the other tribes were calling him
the father of the Young Camel was proving to be a different person than who they thought.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق), then went out to the Sahabah(صحابه) after the delegates left
and he told them:
إن الارض كافرة، وقد رأى وفدهم منكم قلة،
وإنكم لا تدرون ليلا يأتون أم نهارا
وأدناهم منكم على بريد، وقد كان القوم يؤملون أن نقبل منهم ونوادعهم
وقد أبينا عليهم، فاستعدوا وأعدوا
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) after he gathered the Muslims. He said;
The land has sunk into disbelief and their delegation has seen that you are few
so that you would be unaware whether you were approached by day or by night.
The nearest of them is only a stage from you,
the people who are hoping that we would accept them and be reconciled with them
but we refuse them and dissolve their treaty, so get ready.
He said: They wanted to make a treaty with us, we refused
and they've came to Madina and they have seen how few we are.
Because when they saw the army of Usama(أسامه) they thought that
there might be this huge army in Madina
but now when they came to Madina, they saw the reality.
There weren't many people there.
So, the weakness of the Muslims was exposed in terms of their lack of numbers.
And he said: Be ready, because they could attack us at any moment.
What was the plan of As-Siddique رضي الله عنه to defend Islam.?
Number one, he had the soldiers sleep in the Masjid(مسجد) camp in the Masjid(مسجد),
so that they could be ready at any moment to immediately protect Al-Madina.
He doesn't want everybody to be in their house.
He had the force ready, and they established their base in Al-Masjid Al-Nabwi(ألمسجد النبوي)
that's number one.
Number two,
he had guards on all of the mountain passes on all of the routes leading into Madina,
so that they would give an advanced warning to the Muslims in Madina, in case there's any attack.
And he appointed the Umara'a(أمراء) over these guards Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب)
and Az-Zubair Bin Awwam(ألزبير بن عوام), Talha Bin Obaid-Ellah(طلحة بن عبيدالله)
and Sa'ad Bin Abi Waqas(سعدإبن أبي وقاص), Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف)
and Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود).
These were the heads of the security guards that were surrounding Madina from every direction.
And number three, he tried to mobilize the Arab tribes surrounding Madina, who are still Muslim
like Ghaffar(غفار) and Juhaina(جهينه) and Aslam(أسلم).
And these Bedouin tribes did support,
for example, Juhaina(جهينه) they sent many camels into Madina
and they put them under the hand of Al-Khalifah رضي الله عنه to use however, he sees appropriate
so they did offer some help.
Within three days, as the Khalifah(خليفه) expected
the tribes who were just in Madina, did prepare an army to attack.
And they made their move, so the Sahabah(صحابه) who faced them were fighting them on camels.
Now the enemy has found this innovative way of scaring the camels.
They use these like balloons made out of skin, animal skin.
Balloons that they would fill and then they would throw these balloons
and roll them in front of the camels
and they would kick them, so these would roll down in front of the camels
and that would terrify the camels and the camels would runaway.
It was so bad that the camels just turned around and went back to Madina,
along with all of the Sahabah(صحابه).
So the camels got out of control and the Sahabah(صحابه) weren't able to bring them back.
This made the enemy, think that the Muslims are weak and that they ran away.
So, it was the Qadar(قَدَر) of Allah that, they be dragged to Madina, that way.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه in the meanwhile, was preparing a huge army
and he led it by himself, and they went out under the cover of night to ambush the enemy
and the enemy did not know that the Muslims were coming,
they didn't expect that the Muslims will come out to meet them.
And suddenly out of nowhere, the Muslims attack them from every direction
right before Fajr(فجر), when it was still dark
so by the time the sun was rising, the enemy was already turning their backs and running away.
And that was the first victory that occurred,
and that was, what they have called Bidaya-Tul-Fath(بدائية الفتح)
that was the beginning of the opening.
The news spread, so in that same night the Sahabah(صحابه) in Madina would see some people coming to Madina
and they would always assume that it is an enemy attacking
and Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه tell them: No! This is good news.
And they would find out that it is people bringing their Zaka'at(زكوة)
some of these tribes coming to pay their Zaka'at(زكوة).
One tribe came and delivered their Zaka'at(زكوة) in the beginning of the night
a second tribe middle of the night, and third tribe, towards the last hours of the night.
So immediately within one day, things were changing, and turning around.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه went to fight again.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنه and the Sahabah(صحابه), they went to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and said;
You should not go out and fight yourself, appoint somebody to lead the armies
because if you are killed, that will be very difficult for the Muslims
and that will be a great victory for the enemies of Allah.
Have somebody else, go out and lead the battles - the armies.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said: No! I'm not gonna stand behind
and I'm gonna give you an example, through my own self.
So the old man, who has already passed the age of 60
is leading the war by himself and fighting
and he did that in three consecutive campaigns رضي الله عنه.
Zarrar Ibn Azwar(ضراربن الأزور)
to show you how Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was handling the situation.
I mean, these are events that are happening so fast.
The death of Rasool Allah ﷺ, the appointment of the Khalifah(خليفه), the Riddah(ردَّة)
the war against the Murtaddeen(مرتدين).
The news coming from every corner of Arabia about armies amassing and getting prepared to attack the Muslims
and how would Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) deal with all of this disastrous news
that was coming from every direction.
Zarrar Ibn Azwar(ضراربن الأزور), who was the one leading the campaign towards the north east against Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحه ألأسدي),
Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحه ألأسدي) is one of three who claimed to be Prophets during the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and the situation only got worse, when Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away.
The Da'wah(دعوة) of Tulaiha(طليحه) was spreading like wildfire.
So his army was increasing every day, he was getting more and more soldiers.
So Zarrar Ibn Azwar(ضراربن الأزور), a Sahabi(صحابي), who was appointed to lead an army to fight Tulaiha(طليحه).
He would come back to Al-Madina and deliver news to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
And he would say;
فما رأيت أحدا  ليس رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم  أملا بحرب شعواء من أبى بكر
فجعلنا نخبره ولك أنَّما نخبره بما له لا ما عليه
He said: I've never seen anybody, after Rasool Allah ﷺ
who was so calm in the face of disaster like Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
I would deliver to him the news Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحه ألأزدي)
and it would appear as if I'm giving him glad tidings and not giving him bad news.
So they would ask Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه, they would later tell him,
لقد نزل بك مالو نزل بالجبال لهاضها وبالبحار لغاظها ومانراك ضعفت
They told him: You are carrying a load on your shoulder that was so heavy
if it was placed on top of a mountain it would break it
and if it was placed on the oceans, it would empty them of their water.
and we never saw that you became weak.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said;
I never felt fear in my heart after that day in the cave with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
That day I was afraid, I told Rasool Allah ﷺ:
If one of them would just look beneath their feet, they would see us
Rasool Allah ﷺ told me what do you think about two and Allah is their third
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says;
فأنزل سكينته عليه
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has brought down His tranquility,
so the tranquility came on both Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
So how can Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) feel any fear
after Allah سبحانه وتعالى has brought his tranquility on both of them in the cave.
He said: I never felt fear after that and that's how calm and steadfast he was, in the face of all of these storms.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه adopted many methods in fighting Al-Murtaddeen(ألمرتدين).
He sent 11 armies to fight in different corners.
He also employed the method of strengthening the Muslims within the apostate tribes
because apostasy wasn't like a movement where everybody just gave up Islam.
In some cases, an entire tribe would give up Islam.
In some cases, the majority of the tribe.
In some cases the minority of the tribe.
In some cases, tribes were firm and steadfast on Islam.
So whenever Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه would hear about a tribe that became apostate
he would try to establish links with the Muslims within
and delegate to them the responsibility of bringing the tribe back to Islam and fighting them
because he wants to reduce the load on Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار) and Muhajireen(مهاجرين).
The Muhajireen(مهاجرين) and Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار) cannot fight in the same time, each and every tribe
so he tried to delegate it, for example, with Yemen.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه did not sent any army to deal with Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي)
rather he tried to establish links with the Mo'mineen(مؤمنين), who were within.
Because he wanted to devote the strongest forces to fight the most dangerous Riddah(ردَّة)
which was the Riddah(ردَّة) of Musailimah Al-Kazzab(مسيلمه لألكذاب)
and Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحه ألأزدي) at the time.
Because you have Musaylimah(مسيلمه), you have Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحه ألأزدي)
and you had Sajjah(سجاح) in the north and then you had Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) in Yemen.
He also used the method of letters, he would send out letters, giving Da'wah(دعوة) to the Murtaddeen(مرتدين)
and making it clear to them that I can expect nothing from you, less than Islam.
And if you don't come back to the folds of the religion, then you're going to face the sword.
He was making those terms very clear to them.
Let's start with Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي),
Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) was from Al-Ans(ألعنس) close to San'a(صنعاء) in Yemen.
He claimed Prophethood during the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ in the 10th year of Hijrah(هجرة).
And he used to receive Wahii(وحي) from Shiyateen(شياطين)
the man was connected to Devil's, he was possessed by demons.
He started out his mission in the beginning, secretly, and then he announced it
and suddenly, his Da'wah(دعوة) was spreading very fast.
In the beginning it engulfed all of his people of Al-Ans(ألعنس), and then it started spreading out
and he advanced towards San'a(صنعاء).
And he fought with Shahar Bin Badhan(شهر بن باذان).
When Yemen became Muslim - San'a(صنعا) was ruled by a Persian family.
Because Yemen was invaded for some time Abraha(أبرهة) invaded Yemen, Abraha Al-Ashram(أبرهة ألأشرم).
So then they sought assistance from the Persian Empire to help them.
So, the Persian sent an army to Yemen, which fought Abraha(أبرهة) and defeated him
and then they took over, so there were remnants of Persians, in Yemen.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ sent them letters inviting them to Islam
these Persians became Muslim.
Badhan(باذان), who was governing San'a(صنعاء) at that time, he became Muslim
and Rasool Allah ﷺ approved him in his position of being the governor of San'a(صنعاء).
And Rasool Allah ﷺ appointed him to govern all of Yemen.
When he passed away, Rasool Allah ﷺ split up, Yemen in to different states
and his son continued ruling over San'a(صنعاء), his son, his name is Shahar(شهر).
Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) was now marching towards San'a(صنعاء).
And he met with Shahar Bin Badhan(شهر بن باذان) in Shuoob(شعوب), which is next to San'a(صنعاء).
And he defeated him, so now Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) is ruling over San'a(صنعاء).
And then he was sending his army so he was able to take over Najraan(نجران)
and he was able to reach into Lahaj(لحج).
So, his control was getting larger and larger.
Rasool Allah ﷺ sent a message to his Umara'a(أمراء) in Yemen
to deal with the situation of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي), either by deception or by brute force.
Meaning you either take care of him from inside
or you meet him through outside forces and armies.
When Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) killed Shahar Bin Badhan(شهر بن باذان) the Persian king of Yemen.
He married his wife, Azaad(آزاد).
And he tried to establish close relationships with Al-Abnaa(ألأبناء)
Alabnaa(ألأبناء) are the Persians in Yemen, among them was Firoze(فيروز) and others.
And the head of the Army of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) his name is Qais(قيس).
So now Firoze(فيروز) started a plot, thinking about the plot to get rid of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) from within
rather than facing him with armies.
Why don't we try to take care of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) himself by assassinating him
because the whole problem would be solved if this one figure is eliminated.
So Firoze(فيروز) was able to gather around him, some like minded people
who were still Muslim firm on Islam and willing to sacrifice for Islam.
And then they went to Qais(قيس), the head of the army of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي)
they heard that there's a dispute going on between the two.
So they went to Qais(قيس) and they told him,
We are willing to work with you to get rid of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) and Qais(قيس) agreed.
Now Qais(قيس) might not have necessarily agreed because he wants to go back to Islam
it is because he had a political dispute over power with Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي).
And he was afraid that Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) would get rid of him
and then Firoze(فيروز) consulted with the wife of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي)
Azaad(آزاد), the Persian woman.
He said: This is our plan, how can you help us.
She said: Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) is always surrounded by guards
they never leave him alone, until he gets into this particular room.
So there is no way for you to reach Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي)
unless you come from this direction and she gave them a layout of the palace.
This particular room, where Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) sleeps with his family.
The only place that is free from security guards, there is a way to access it, from the outside.
And she gave them the plan and the layout and the way of how to get into this room.
Now, since it's late at night,
she said: I will place for you in this particular room some light a lamp and weapons.
Now, Firoze(فيروز) was able to get in and out and meet with Azaad(آزاد) because he was her cousin.
So Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) wouldn't suspect.
So now, Azaad(آزاد) helped them out
and they decided that we're going to meet this particular night.
So Firoze(فيروز) along with two other men they broke into this room
and as soon as they wanted to get the lamp and the weapons
Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) came to Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) when he was asleep
and he made him sit up upright and speak to Firoze(فيروز).
Now Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) he himself was asleep
but this was Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) speaking on his tongue.
And he was saying Firoze(فيروز), I know what you want to do
Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) was a huge and powerful well built Man.
Firoze(فيروز) was terrified by Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) speaking to him
and he thought he initially thought that it is actually Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) speaking to him
but it was the devil, speaking to him.
So he said: If I retreat now then our plan is over with
and he doesn't have time to go and grab the weapons.
So he just jumped on Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي)
and got on top of him and grabbed his head and broke his neck and then he walked out.
Azaad(آزاد) thought that he's running away.
She told him: Where are you going?
She didn't know that he was killed.
He said: I'm going to go and tell my two companions.
So he went on call them from the other room and they came in
to find that Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) wasn't dead yet.
He was tossing around in the room, even though his neck was broken.
Allah Ho Alam(الله أعلم) it was the Jinn(جن) inside of him or what
but he was tossing around in the room.
So Firoze(فيروز) said: I tried to grab him, I couldn't.
The man was so strong and powerful, who just jumping around
so the other two had to come and grab him for me
until I grabbed the knife and I beheaded him.
So then we waited in the room until it was Fajr(فجر), we just stayed in there
By the way, Firoze(فيروز) said: When he cut the head of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي)
he made the very loud roar
so the guards came running and they said: What's happening.?
So the wife of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) said:
Don't worry, the prophet is receiving revelation.
Anyway they waited in the room, till it was Fajr(فجر) - and they went out and made Adhaan(آذان),
which was not heard in a long time.
So the soldiers are all amazed
and that was a sign for the soldiers of Firoze(فيروز) when they hear Adhaan(آذان) to come.
So the armies of Firoze(فيروز) attacked
and they threw out the head of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) in front of his supporters
and that was the end of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي).
The same night, the assassination of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) took place
Jibreel عليه السّلام went to Muhammadﷺ and gave him the news.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ the next day in the morning is telling the Sahabah(صحابه)
Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) has been killed
and he was killed by a blessed man from a blessed family.
They said: Who was it? He said: Firoze(فيروز)
So Firoze(فيروز) was a blessed man
and his family was blessed, because this was a plan that was mostly done by these Persian men
plus, Azaad(آزاد) the Persian woman.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ called it a blessed family.
And by the way, this story of Firoze(فيروز) is one evidence that the Fuqahaa(فقهاء) use
to support overthrowing a Murtadd(مرتد) government through means of assassination.
Because Yemen was ruled by Islam,
and then you have Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) a Murtadd(مرتد) ruling over Yemen
and Rasool Allah ﷺ sanctioned what they did.
However, when the news of the death of Rasool Allah ﷺ came to Yemen
the remnants of the army of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) started to revolt again.
This time the Riddah(ردَّة) was worse because it was popping up in different places
in Najraan(صنعاء), in San'a(صنعاء) in Hazara Moat(حضرالموت) in Kinda(كندة), in Mahra(مهرة)
in Lahaj(لحج), in Aden(عدن)
just as it was in the rest of the Arabian Peninsula.
Wherever you had new Muslims, who were still weak in their faith you had Riddah(ردَّة)
Qais(قيس), who was the head of the army of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي)
who joined in the plot to kill Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي)
joined with the forces of Al-Murtaddeen(مرتدين). Why?
Because Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه appointed Firoze(فيروز), to be the leader of San'a(صنعاء)
and Qais(قيس) did not like that - so he broke ranks
and he joined with the forces of Al-Murtaddeen(مرتدين).
So now, Al-Muhajir Bin Umayyah(مهاجر إبن أمية) and Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ إبن جبل)
and other Sahabah(صحابه) who were in Yemen, they had to start fighting the Murtaddeen(مرتدين) in different areas.
And slowly, they were defeating
all of the forces of Riddah(ردَّة), until the whole country fell under the rule of Shariah(شريعة) again.
So that is the Riddah(ردَّة) of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي)
which again started during the life of Rasool Allah ﷺ
I made it very brief, I didn't go into the details.
First of all because there's a lot of names and places and events, it might be confusing.
Second, our purpose is to learn lessons.
So wherever I find that there are strong lessons I would mention to you the event or the incident
because again we're talking about Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق)
and the era of Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق)
and if we're going to talk about everything is going to take a very long time.
A few events that happened in Yemen
and then we'll move on to the Riddah(ردَّة) of Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأزدي).
The example of the righteous woman, and the evil woman.
Azaad(آزاد) was an example of a righteous woman
who sacrificed for her religion
like Asiyah Bint Muzahim(آسيه بنت مزاحم), the wife of Firaun(فرعون) did.
Asiyah Bint Muzahim(آسيه بنت مزاحم) was a wife of Firaun(فرعون)
the most powerful king on the face of the earth
she had everything that a lover of Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) would want.
She was living in the greatest palace, the palace which was mentioned in Qur'an,
الْأَنْهَارُ تَجْرِي مِن تَحْتِي ۖ
That rivers are flowing beneath me, under me.
She had all of the wealth that she would want but that didn't satisfy her.
And she was asking Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to replace her with a Palace in Jannah(جنة)
rather than this Palace on earth.
Azaad(آزاد) was the wife of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي)
the most powerful man in Yemen during his time, but she was a Muslim,
and she described her husband, Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) by saying,
Allah has not created any human being, more dislike to me than Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي).
I never hated anybody in my life like I hated this man.
She said: He does not do any good and all of his actions are evil.
And she sacrificed, and what she did, she could have paid for it dearly.
If the plot was uncovered by Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي), she would have been killed.
And Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) was very vicious, in his treatment of Muslims
he would cut them into pieces, and let them die a slow death.
on the other hand, you have women of evil.
Examples of both Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ gave the example of Asiyah(آسية) in Qur'an
alongside the example of the wife of Lut(لوط) and Nooh(نوح)
and both examples existed in Yemen.
Whenever the rule of Islam, comes to a place there are going to be people who will not be happy with it,
not everybody will vote for Islam.
There are going to be people, who hate the law of Allah
and believe that it is restricting their freedoms, and their liberty.
And these people tend to be part of the aristocracy.
People who don't want any limitations on their enjoyment and Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and their pleasure, and their sensations.
There were people like this all over, in every state, which fell under the law of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
In Hazar-al-Maot(حضرالموت) there was a movement called the movement of the prostitutes.
This was a movement of more than 20 prostitutes from different villages in Hazar-al-Maot(حضرالموت)
who, when Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away they covered their hands and Hinnah(هنا)
and they sang songs to celebrate the death of Rasool Allah ﷺ
because these were women of evil they felt that Islam restricted their life
they were like flies, who can only survive on filth.
And when Islam came and took away their filth, they felt that they were starving to death.
They felt that they could not breath, they were suffocating.
So when Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away, they were happy and they were celebrating.
So one of the men of Hazar-al-Maot(حضرالموت), sent a poem to Al-Khalifah(خليفه), Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
describing the situation and asking for help.
So Al-Khalifah(خليفه) sent a letter to his governor over Hazar-al-Maot(حضرالموت)
Al-Muhajir Ibn Abi Umayyah(ألمهاجر بن أبي أمية) and told him,
I command you to take an army, and to amputate the arms of these women
and if anybody stands in your way, then deliver to them the message of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
and Da'wah(دعوة) to Islam, and if they refuse then fight them.
Because Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه knew that these women are not speaking on their own behalf,
they are representing a certain segment of the society.
And this segment of society will rush to defend them
because evil always comes together to support itself whenever Al-Haqq(ألحق) attacks it.
So all of these people of evil, who felt that Islam is depriving them of their way of life.
They came together to protect these women
and they marched forward to fight Al-Muhajir(ألمهاجر).
So Al-Muhajir(ألمهاجر) spoke to them and gave them the Da'wah(دعوة) of Allah
and told them the consequences of their actions, many of them agreed.
And then, Al-Muhajir(ألمهاجر) fought the rest
and then he went ahead and amputated the arms of these women
and many of them died because of that and some other left Hazar-al-Maot(حضرالموت)
and settled into Al-Kufa(ألكوفه) and other places, anyway.
So every age and time there will be people who will decide to fight Al-Haqq(ألحق)
until the last moment.
There was a Karamah(كرامة) that happened to one of the Awliyya(أولياء) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
Abu Muslim Al-Khaulani(أبومسلم ألخولاني).
Abu Muslim Al-Khaulani رضي الله عنه is one of the Taba'een(تابعين)
Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) captured him and told him,
Do you testify that I am the messenger of Allah.
He said: I can't hear you,
He said: Do you testify that Muhammad(محمد) is the Messenger of Allah,
He said: Yes,
He said: Do you testify that I am the messenger of Allah!
He said: I cannot hear you,
Do you testify that Muhammad(محمد) is the Messenger of Allah.
He said: Yes! And he repeated that three times.
So Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) ordered that he be burned at the stake.
So they burnt Abu Muslim Al-Khaulani(أبومسلم ألخولاني)
And Abu Muslim Al-Khaulani(أبومسلم ألخولاني) came out walking without any harm whatsoever
only the rope that they tied him with.
So the followers of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي) said: You have to force him to leave your land
otherwise he will be Fitnah(فِتْنَه) for the people.
This miracle might cause the people to go back to Islam
so we want you to send him out of the land.
So he went to Madina and he came into the Masjid(مسجد), and he was praying
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Where's this man from? They said: He's from Yemen.
So he called him after he finished his Salah(صلاة)
he said: I want you to tell me about the man who was burnt in the fire by Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي).
He said: That man is Abdullah Bin Thaub(عبدالله بن ثوب)
his name is Abdullah Bin Thaub(عبدالله بن ثوب).
He said: Is it you?
I ask you in the name of Allah, is it you? He said: Yes! It's me.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه immediately hugged him and started crying
and said: Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدلله), Praise be to Allah, who made me live
until I see a man whom Allah سبحانه وتعالى saved from the fire just as He saved Ibrahim عليه السّلام.
He said: Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدلله), who made me live until I can see
a member of the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ, who was saved from the fire.
Just like Ibrahim عليه السّلام was saved from the fire.
So this was a Karmah(كرامة) that happened to a follower of Muhammadﷺ.
And it is similar to a miracle that occurred to a Nabi(نَبِي) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Abu Muslim Al-Khaulani(أبومسلم ألخولاني) was one of the fascinating figures among the Taba'een رضي الله عنه.
There are many stories about him but I'll just mention one about his death.
He was fighting alongside Bishr Bin Arta(بِشربن أرطاة) against the Romans.
So his Ameer(أمير) was Bishr Bin Arta(بِشربن أرطاة)
and Abu Muslim Al-Khaulani(أبومسلم ألخولاني) was injured.
So, before he died he called the Ameer(أمير) of the Army, Bishr Bin Arta(بِشربن أرطاة) and he told him:
When I die, I want you to bury me, the furthest into the land of the enemy
I want my grave, to be ahead of the graves of all of the other Shuhadaa(شهداء).
And then I want you to appoint me as an Ameer(أمير) over the Shuhadaa(شهداء)
and to give me a banner of war that you burry with me
so that on the Day of Judgment when we are resurrected
I can carry that banner and lead the Shuhadaa(شهداء) on the Day of Judgment.
So he doesn't want his Jihad(جهاد) to stop and Duniyah(دُنِيَّا)
he wants to continue it in Aakhirah(آخرة), he wants to come on the Day of Judgment carrying the banner,
and leading the Shuhadaa(شهداء) behind him.
So this is a Karamaa(كرامة) that happened with Abu Muslim Al-Khaulani رضي الله عنه.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) was very harsh with some of the apostates
and he showed clemency to some others, depending on the situation there was not one standard.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه would make a judgment, according to the situation.
Whenever he would see that there's potential for some people to serve Islam in the future
he would allow them to go.
So he gave clemency to Amr Bin Ma'diaqrib(عمروبن معديكرب)
and Qais Bin Muradi(قيس بن مرادي), the one who was the head of the army of Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(ألأسود ألعنسي).
He set him free and also Al-Ash'as Bin Qais(ألعشعث بن قيس)
who fought against Sahabah رضي الله عنهم in Hazaral Moat(حضرالموت).
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله)
it was the vision of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه that he gives these three men clemency
because these three men played some very important roles
during Jihad(جهاد) in the time of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه.
See in the time of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) he gave his instructions
that nobody, who apostated should be allowed to participate in the Fath(فتح).
When the wars of apostasy were over
and now the armies were sent to fight against the Persian and Roman Empire
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) gave instructions
that none of the Murtaddeen(مرتدين) should participate in these armies.
It wasn't until the time of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه, was this overruled.
And there were some reasons for that
if we have time In sha Allah(إن شاءالله), we'll talk about that, later.
Another incidents worth mentioning
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) has sent Ikrimah Bin Abi Jahl(عكرمة بن أبي جهل)
the son of Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل), Ikrimah(عكرمة), who became Muslim
he sent him to lead an army of 700, horsemen, to the land of Musailima(مسيلمة)
Ikrimah(عكرمة) was in a hurry, so he got into a premature confrontation with Bannu Hanifa(بنوحنيفة),
and he was defeated
The news reached to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) sent him a very urgent message telling him,
I don't want to see! Do not come back!
Because that will weaken the morale of our forces
and I want you to immediately leave and go to Yemen
and to support the Muslims who are there, and to enter from Oman(عمان).
What was the wisdom behind this?
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه did not want the Muslims, who lost in the war against the forces of Musailima(مسيلمة)
to meet with any army that's going to the same direction,
because then they would share the news, and they would speak about the forces of the enemy
and that would weaken the morale of the Muslims, who are going towards that direction.
So he said immediately leave, and I don't want you to come back to Madina
because this will weaken the morale of the people of Madina, go to Oman(عمان).
You're going to fight a different battle, different field with different people.
So go to Oman(عمان) and he came through Oman(عمان), Al-Mahra(ألمحرة) and then joined forces
with the others Sahabah(صحابه) in Yemen.
So that shows the wisdom in the leadership of Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق).
When Muadh Bin Jabal(معاذبن جبل) came back to Madina
because he was appointed by Rasool Allah ﷺ to go to Yemen to teach the people Islam.
So when they came back
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), his way was that whenever a governor would come back, he would sit down with him
and go through all the records,
and he would hold him accountable to everything that happened within the term of his governceship, Hissab(حساب).
When that happened Muadh Bin Jabal(معاذبن جبل) said;
You want me to go through two reckonings, reckoning with Allah and a reckoning with you.
I will never assume a position of leadership with you anymore
and you never wanted to become Ameer(أمير) after that.
He said: I'm already going to be held accountable by Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
and now you want to hold me accountable
but that was the way of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) carried on, implementing the same rules.
We're done with the Riddah(ردَّة) in Yemen.
We move on to the Riddah(ردَّة) of Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأسدي).
This was among Asd(أسد), Ghatafaan(غطفان) and Abs(عبس) and Dhabiyaan(ذبيان)
the four Arab tribes.
Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأسدي) was a Muslim.
He and a delegation from Asd(أسد) came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and they said;
We have came to pledge our allegiance to you, we are Muslim.
And you didn't ask us to come, we came by ourselves.
And we became Muslim, and they went on and on bragging about it.
So Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ revealed the Ayah(آية);
يَمُنُّونَ عَلَيْكَ أَنْ أَسْلَمُوا ۖ قُل لَّا تَمُنُّوا عَلَيَّ إِسْلَامَكُم ۖ بَلِ اللَّهُ يَمُنُّ عَلَيْكُمْ أَنْ هَدَاكُمْ لِلْإِيمَانِ إِن كُنتُمْ صَادِقِينَ۝
They consider it a favor to you, that they have accepted Islam.
Say, do not consider your Islam a favor to Me
rather Allah has conferred the favor upon you that He has guided you to the faith
if you should be truthful.
This is in Hujraat(حجرات) verse 17.
It is the favor of Allah on you, you shouldn't come and brag about it to Muhammadﷺ
by saying that we have done you a favor by becoming Muslim.
It is a favor from Allah that He allowed you to become Muslim
that He guided to the straight path anyway.
Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأسدي), later on changed his mind and he claimed to be a prophet.
Because when they were in the desert, and they had no water
someone riding on the camel of Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأسدي) found water,
so they considered to be a blessed camel, belonging to a blessed person
he took advantage of that and he claimed that he is a prophet of Allah.
And again he would make this funny, Su'ar(سوئر), just like Musailimah Al-Kazzab(مسيلمة ألكذاب)
Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأسدي) was a very courageous man, strong fighter, very skilled leader.
So, that claim was very dangerous to come from such a man
Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأسدي) convinces his people Asd(أسد)
and then they got into a agreement with Ghatafan(غطفان), so Ghatafan(غطفان) join in
and then they were reinforced by Abs(عبس) and Dhabiyan(ذبيان).
So now I have these four huge tribes, all under the leadership of Tulaiha(طليحة).
Now by the way, with all of these new prophets that are springing up everywhere.
It's not that the Arabs were religious people, it's not that they had conviction in these prophets
the nature of the Bedouin people is that they are not religious
and people think I mean, you have this assumption that the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) were very religious
and that's why they were very antagonistic towards Islam, that was the furthest from the truth.
The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), were not very religious
and they were also very tolerant towards religion.
And this is something that people don't realize.
In general, the Arabs were among the most tolerant people, when it comes to religious practice.
In other parts of the world, it was expected that everybody follow the same religion
Homogeneous societies in Persia, Zoroastrians.
Among the Romans, they would persecute the non Christian
the Jews were persecuted in the Holy Land
so it was expected that everybody follows the same religion.
while in Arabia, like for example in the Yemen, you had Jews, You had Christians
with these prostitutes, the most famous among them and the leader of this movement
which was called the movement of prostitutes, was a Jew.
Her name was Hirr Bin Yamin Al-Yahoodia(هربنت يامين اليهودية)
and in fact this prostitute she set a record in prostitution
that she became an example, they would say;
أذنا من هر
Whenever a woman would be accused with this, they would say
that she is more of a prostitute than Hirr(هر).
So you had Jews in Yemen, you had Christians, you had pagan worshippers
and you had Zoroastrians the Persians, and people were very tolerant about it.
In Makkah Waraqah Bin Nofal(ورقه بن نوفل) was a Christian
Zaid(زيد) was a Hanifi(حنيفي) following the religion of Ibrahim عليه السّلام
and then you had people who didn't follow religion at all, Ad-Dahriyoon(ألدهريون).
In fact, Ukaaz(عكاظ), where the speakers would go and talk about everything
was no different than Hyde Park.
It was a very tolerant society when it came to religion.
Zaid Bin Nufail(زيدبن نفيل) when, he would stand next to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه)
and tell the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), that your religion is false.
لستم على شئ
And he would tell them, you should not sacrifice to these idols, and nobody would harm him.
It was only when the Da'wah(دعوة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ began that they became intolerant.
So, a very tolerant society can become very intolerant when it comes to Islam.
So don't be fooled by what you see,
the people of Makkah turned upside down
one of the most tolerant societies in the world when it comes to religion became the most intolerant.
Why?
Because now they're not just dealing with a religion, they're dealing with the truth.
And they know that when the truth comes, it's either truth or falsehood.
The two cannot coexist, evil can get along with evil, it's just a different brand.
But when it's Al-Haqq(ألحق), it's either Al-Haqq(ألحق) or a Batil(باطل).
So, these tribes were joining Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأزدي) out of nationalism, tribalism.
They didn't want to submit to a man from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
I mean, before it was a Prophet but now Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), who is Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)?
We're not gonna give Baiyah(بَيْعة) to Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق).
Who is he?
So, they came under the banner of Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأسدي).
Now, Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) for this important mission
عقد الراية لِخالد إبن وليد
He gave the Raiyah(راية), the banner to Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد).
The man whom Rasool Allah ﷺ said about, he is a sword of the swords of Allah
which was drawn against Al-Kuffar(ألكفار) and Al-Munafiqeen(مُنافقين).
سيف من سيوف الله سلّه الله على الكفار والمنافقين
He gave the banner to a man, who never ever had one of his banners in war fall down.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) has never ever in his life
whether in Islam or before Islam lost in the battle, never.
He sent him to fight Tulaiha(طليحة).
And Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه told Udae Bin Hatim(عدئ بن حاتم)
go and save your people Tae(طيئ), lest Tulaiha(طليحة) should mislead them.
The tribe of Tae(طيئ), which were neighboring the territory of Tulaiha(طليحة)
had not joined in with Tulaiha(طليحة) yet.
So Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) wants Udae(عديئ), who was the chief of his tribe
to go as soon as possible, and save his people from hellfire.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said;
أدرك قومك لا  يلحقوا بطليحة فيكون دمارهم
Hasten towards your people, and save them from Tulaiha(طليحة)
because that will be their detriment.
For Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) the issue was already done, Tulaiha(طليحة) is going to lose.
So he's telling Udae(عدئ) go and save your people before they perish.
It wasn't a 50, 50 thing for Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) he already knew the results.
If you join Tulaiha(طليحة), you're on the losing side.
So he told Udae(عدئ), go and save them.
And Udae Bin Hatim(عدئ بن حاتم), was a Muslim
who came and pledged his Islam to Rasool Allah ﷺ, so he's among the Sahabah(صحابه)
he was the man who came in, wearing the cross, Udae(عدئ) was a Christian
he was wearing a cross, when it came to meet Muhammadﷺ.
So when Rasool Allah ﷺ saw the cross hanging on his chest. He said:
اتَّخَذُوا أَحْبَارَهُمْ وَرُهْبَانَهُمْ أَرْبَابًا مِّن دُونِ اللَّهِ
They have taken their rabbis and their priests gods besides Allah.
Udae(عدئ) said: We do not consider our priests to be gods
Udae(عدئ) is trying to correct the information of Rasool Allah ﷺ about Christianity.
He said: We do not consider our priests to be God.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
These priests, didn't they make, what was Halal(حلال), Haram(حرام)
and what was Haram(حرام), Halal(حلال).
What Allah made legal they made illegal, and what Allah made illegal they made legal.
Udae(عدئ) said: Yes! He said that is worshipping them besides Allah.
When St. Paul says that all of the law of the Bible is dissolved now
you don't have to follow the law of the Torah(توراة).
What is that? It's making Haram(حرام), Halal(حلال).
When Eesa Ibn Maryam(عيسى إبن مريم) says that I came to fulfill the law
Jot by Jot, Dot by Dot, Letter by Letter
and then St. Paul comes on over rules that
and says; No! You don't have to follow the law,
that is worshiping Him, besides Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Going back to the issue of the religion of the Arabs, the northern tribes were Christian.
So Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was asked about eating their meat because they're a Christian.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said;
They know nothing about Christianity but drinking wine, thats all, they know about it.
ليس لهم من النصراني ألأشرب من الخمر
These people are not religious, they're not into religion.
So, Udae Bin Hatim(عدئ بن حاتم) went to plead with his people
and he told Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد): Give me three days
because Khalid(خالد) was ready to attack Tae(طئ)
Udae(عدئ) said: Wait, because Tae(طئ) have already sent some fighters to join with Tulaiha(طليحة),
so they were already stuck not all of them but they have already sent some of their men to fight alongside Tulaiha(طليحة).
So, Khalid(خالد) was ready to attack them. Udae(عدئ) said:
Just give me three days, and then he told Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
isn't it better that I saved them from hellfire.?
Would you rather have them go to hell, or be saved from hell, and not fight you.
So Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said: I will give you three days
so Udae(عدئ) went, his people said:
We are never going to pledge allegiance to the father of the young camel, Abul Faseel(أبوالفصيل).
Because I said, that Bakr(بكر) means young camel that's full of vigor
but they were calling him Abul Faseel(أبوالفصيل), Faseel(فصيل) is a newborn camel, that is weak.
So they were nicknaming Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), the father of the weak camel,
they considered him to be a weak man. They said:
We, the people Tae(طئ), you want us to pledge allegiance to the father of the young camel.
Udae Bin Hatim(عدئ بن حاتم) said: Listen, his armies are gonna start coming to your land one after another,
and they will teach you a lesson that is the father of the stallion and not the father of the young camel.
Listen to me, and give your Baiyah(بَيْعة) to him.
They refused.
He stayed there, trying, going back and forth negotiating with them convincing them for three days
until he was able to convince one branch of Tae(طئ).
Tae(طئ) were made of two branches, he convinced one.
He went back to Khalid(خالد) and said:
Give me some time, because I've saved one branch, give me some time to save the other.
Khalid(خالد) said: Go ahead.
He went tried his best with them and he was able to pull them out of the alliance with Tulaiha(طليحة).
Now they said: We have to call our fighters from the army of Tulaiha(طليحة)
because if Tulaiha(طليحة) hears that we are Muslim now, he's gonna kill our men
and they were able to withdraw those also.
So Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) says that
Udae Bin Hatim(عدئ بن حاتم) was considered to be the most blessed man for his people.
He saved them from hellfire.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) sent out two of the Sahabah(صحابه)
on a reconnaissance mission to go and gather information about the army of Tulaiha(طليحة).
These two companions were Ukasha Bin Muhsan(عكاشة بن محصن)
and Sabit Bin Qais Bin Shammas(ثابت بن قيس بن شماس)
two among the prominent Sahabah(صحابه).
Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأزدي) and his brother were out, also, spying on the Muslims.
Tulaiha(طليحة) again, was a very courageous man, he went out by himself, he and his brother alone
and they killed Ukasha(عكاشة) and Sabit Bin Qais(ثابت بن قيس).
So when they didn't come back, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and the army went to investigate
and they came and found the two bodies of the Sahabah(صحابه)
it says in the book of history that that was a very great setback for the Muslims.
It hurt them a lot, to lose two of the great companions of Rasool Allah ﷺ
in a moment, just like that.
So it was very difficult moment for the Muslims.
But Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) made his move, and they attacked, and they succeeded in defeating Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألسدي).
Now Tulaiha(طليحة) among his alliance was Oyeyna Bin Hasan(عيينة بن حصن)
Oyeyna Bin Hasan(عيينة بن حصن) was among the men, who came and gave pledge of allegiance to Rasool Ullah
and then they broke it and came again, these men would go back and forth
the Bedouins in and out.
So Oyeyna Bin Hasan(عيينة بن حصن) he made an alliance with Tulaiha(طليحة).
So, while the fighting was going on, Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأزدي) was sitting in his tent,
waiting for revelation to come to him.
So Oyeyna(عيينة) come to him and said: Did you receive Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) yet, he said: No!
Went and fought, he came back, did Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) come yet, No!
He came third time. Did Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) come, he said: Yes!
What did he tell you? He said: I'm giving you a millstone and some great news
Oyeyna(عيينة) was not waiting for such a revelation he was waiting for something else, tell us what to do.?
He said: Well, you're going to get some great news. Oyeyna(عيينة) left
and he told all of his fighters, to just leave.
And that was the beginning of the end for Tulaiha(طليحة)
When Tulaiha(طليحة) realized that he's losing.
He and his brother and his wife and some of his close friends, mounted their camels and horses and ran away to Iraq and Ash-Sham(ألشام).
And that was the end of Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأسدي).
Now, the news reached Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), this was a great victory.
He sent a letter to Khalid(خالد) telling him.
May that which Allah has granted you by way of blessings, increase for you.
Fear Allah in your affairs for verily, Allah is with those, who are pious and who do good works
take seriously the Command of Allah and be not lenient.
And whoever you lay your hands over from the disbelievers, who fought the Muslims
then severely punished them and make them as an example to warn another.
So kill whomever you like of those, who showed enmity to Allah, or who opposed Him.
If you think there will be some benefit in doing so.
So, due to these orders from Al-Khalifah(ألخليفه) to severely punish the Murtaddeen(مرتدين)
and to make an example out of them.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) remained in the territory for entire month
going up and down, right and left, capturing the Murtaddeen(مرتدين)
and killing them by burning them in the fire, stoning them to death
throwing them from mountaintops, throwing them into wells
and piercing them with arrows, very harsh punishment
but he was doing it to set an example to the rest of the Murtaddeen(مرتدين)
that Riddah(ردَّة) will not be tolerated.
Al-Fujja'a(ألفجاء) was one of these man who came to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
And he said: I'm going to fight the Murtaddeen(مرتدين), Give me an army
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) provided him with camels and weapons
Al-Fujja'a(ألفجاء), left, and he used the arms and camels that were given to him by the Khalifah(خليفه)
to fight everyone whom he meets Muslim or non Muslim to raid their belongings, a bandit in the desert.
When Al-Khalifah(خليفه) heard of that he sent an army to follow him; in pursue.
They did capture Al-Fujja'a(ألفجاء), and they brought him back to Madina tied up,
so Al-Khalifah(خليفه) ordered that he be burnt to death, in Al-Baqiyyah(ألبقية) in front of everyone
as a punishment for his action.
Tulaiha(طليحة) later became Muslim, he regretted what he did.
And he made Umra(عمرة) during the time of Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق).
So, they told Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), Tulaiha(طليحة) is here.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: What should I do with him, he already became Muslim
but again he was banned from participating in any of the Muslim armies.
Later on, after that he did join in the Fatoohaat(فتوحات)
and he set some amazing examples of courage and bravery Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
So Allah could guide whomever He wishes. This is a man, who claimed prophethood
because of him, hundreds of people went to hellfire and then eventually, he became Muslim.
See with Hidaya(هداية), it's Qadar(قَدَر) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Abu Talib(ابوطالب), who assisted Rasool Allah ﷺ for all of his life goes to hellfire
and Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان), who fights Rasool Allah ﷺ for all of his life becomes a Mo'min(مؤمن).
The Hidaya(هداية) is something in hands on Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Asd(أسد) and Ghatafan(غطفان) regretted what they have done
when Tulaiha(طليحة) has deserted them,
and they came to the Khalifah(خليفه) Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
And they wanted to make Toba(توبة), they came to the Khalifah(خليفه) and said:
We want to make a truce between you and us.
What did the Khalifah(خليفه) say.?
He said: I give you one of two options, that's all what I have for you.
فأما الحرب المجلية أو الخطة المخزية
Either a war of extermination, or a humiliating plan.
They said: We know what the war of extermination means, it means that you get rid of all of us
but what does the humiliating deal mean?
He said: Number one, you give up all of your weapons and you follow the tails of your camels.
You know, to them, stripping them of their weapons is dishonoring them.
Now, with Muslims, it's not an issue people are living like that
they don't see it the problem, but with them even though in the time of Jahiliyyah(جَاهلِيَّة)
living without your weapons is dishonor.
So he says it's like you and your camel are one of the same
without your arms, you are no different than the camel.
He said: You give up your arms and you follow the tails of your camels.
Until Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ puts in the heart of the Khalifah(خليفه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Mo'mineen(مؤمنين)
to accept your apology.
So your hand down all every weapons
and then whenever Allah makes the Khalifah(خليفه) and the Mo'mineen(مؤمنين) accept your apology.
We'll go ahead with it, but I cannot promise you, when.!
Number two, you declare publicly that the ones, who are killed among you are going to hell fire.
And the ones, who are killed among us are going to Jannah(جنة).
I want to hear that from you publicly in front of everyone, in front of your people.
Number three, you pay blood money for the ones, who killed among us
and we pay you nothing for the ones we killed among you.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: I disagree with this last point.
He said: They should not pay us blood money
because the ones, who are killed among us are Shuhadaa(شهداء)
and they died in the path of Allah.
So there is no loss on our behalf - it's an honor for them
but then he said: I like all the rest.
I mean, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), this is what he wants.
I mean this. Yeah, fine! Great!
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه gave them a lesson that he is the father of the stallion and not the father of the young camel.
And they had to agree, give up their weapons, following the tails of their camels
until later on your Khalifah(خليفه) will decide when to accept your apology, what you have done.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ